Albany Central Federation of Labor; Records apap143
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Albany Central Federation of Labor Records
1965-2000
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations--Albany Central Federation of Labor
apap143
3.8 cubic ft.
The collection documents the activities of the Albany Central Federation of Labor (AFL CIO) from 1983 to 2000.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Jospehine Sano donated all materials to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives. 2002 September
Biographical History
The Albany Central Federation of Labor was organized on June 8, 1888 by workers in the Capital District who obtained a charter and formed the organization. The Albany Central Federation of Labor is a local labor council through which the AFL-CIO organizes to build and strengthen the national union movement. On the state level these grassroots organizations function to give working families a voice in their cities, towns, and counties. A primary goal of the labor council is to have workers treated with dignity and paid livable wages.
The American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO) charters almost 570 central labor councils. Their mission is to bring social and economic justice to working people by enabling them to have a voice on the job, in government, in a changing global economy, and in their communities. The AFL-CIO is a voluntary federation of U.S unions and represents more than 13 million working women and men nationwide.
Other goals of the AFL-CIO and its central labor councils are to change the American labor movement by increasing support for local union organizing, expanding the political and legislative action network, building an outreach program to clergy and community, increasing affiliation and participation, and increasing communications with union leaders and members. The Albany Central Federation of Labor has financially supported union strikes and supported and endorsed political candidates.
The officers of the Albany Central Federation of Labor during Sano's tenure were: President Josephine Sano, 1st Vice President Walter Wheeler and Anthony Giagini, 2nd Vice President Elias Amash, Executive Secretary Steve Zahurak and Joseph B. Sano, Sergeant-At-Arms John Kearney, and Treasurer Doug Bullock. Key affiliated unions with the Albany Central Federation of Labor between 1983 and 2000 were the Civil Service Employees Association (C.S.E.A), the American Federation of Teachers (AFT), the American Federation Of State, County And Municipal Employees, (A.F.S.C.M.E), the Communication Workers of America (C.W.A), and the Teamsters.
Josephine Sano grew up in Gloversville, New York, and attended the New York State College for Teachers. She was an educator for forty-seven years. Prior to becoming president of the Albany Central Federation of Labor in 1981, Sano was elected President of the Albany Public Schools Teachers' Association in 1971. Sano was instrumental in the founding of the Capital District Teacher's Unions. Sano received the Taft Institute of Government Scholarship at Russell Sage College in 1972. In 1974 and 1975 Sano was part of the statewide Task Force on Affirmative Action, sponsored by NYSUT. From 1978 to 1979 Sano was a trustee of the Central Federation of Labor. Ms. Sano has been a delegate to AFT conventions many times. In 1987, Sano received the Award of Merit of the Capital District Union Label and Services Trades Council AFL-CIO. Sano, who belongs to the SUNYA Alumni Association, also received an honorary degree from the Cornell School of Industrial Relations. Ms. Sano's tenure as president ended in 2000.
Recently 25 central labor councils in New York were reorganized into five area labor federations and the Albany Central Federation of Labor is a member. This was done with the hope that restructuring the central labor councils would increase the success of the labor movement by combining their strength and resources. Previous presidents have included Ralph Cate, Dominic Spano, Greg Riley, Sam Fresina, Josephine Sano, and Jeffrey Stark.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the activities of the Albany Central Federation of Labor (AFL CIO) from 1983 to 2000. Jospehine Sano became president in 1981. Included in the collection are administrative files such as minutes, constitution, correspondence, annual reports, and financial statements. Records of a previous president were destroyed by their creator.
The numerous publications as well as the correspondence between Josephine Sano and other labor councils is a strong point of the collection. Among the publications are a transcript of the 1992 New York State AFL-CIO Constitutional Convention and a videotape, Deadly Corn, documenting the experiences of workers at a manufacturing company.
Josephine Sano's correspondence gives much insight into how the organization operated and assisted other labor organizations. The United Food & Commercial Workers International Union of the AFL-CIO called for a boycott of national meat packing company John Morrell & Company, which had meat packing plants in more than 10 states. The main reason for the boycott was due to a second wage and benefit cut on workers at the Sioux City plant, but wages had been previously cut at other Morrell locations. In addition to wage cuts, employees were protesting brutal work conditions, short lunches, and "corporate greed." Information about the boycott of John Morrell, which employed more than 4,000 workers, is located in Series 4.
This collection also contains information on Worker's Memorial Day, an annual recognition memorial service for workers killed or injured at work and interim voting records of the state assembly that were used by Albany Central Federation of Labor members to determine which politicians helped the organization and who they would endorse.
Although members on the local and national levels had the same goals they did not necessarily agree on the methods to reach those goals. Included in the collection is the report of former A. Phillip Randolph Institute local president Rufus Collier, which gives insight into conflicts that existed within the organization. The A. Phillip Randolp Institute is a constituency group of the AFL-CIO, which unites unions and diverse communities to strengthen partnerships and improve the standard of living for all workers. The collection does not provide significant information on the family lives of the Albany Central Federation of Labor members or the effect that involvement in a union had on their personal lives.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series: 1. Administrative Files, 1984-2000; 2. Subject Files, 1982-2000; 3. Publications, 1965-2000; 4. Activities, 1983-2000; 5. Correspondence, 1983-2000.
Labor; Albany, New York; Labor policy--New York (State)--Albany; Working class--New York (State)--Albany; Labor unions--New York (State)--Albany; Minutes; Clippings; Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter); American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations--Albany Central Federation of Labor
- Administrative Files, 1984-2000; 1; 1.0 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains minutes and correspondence of the Albany Central Federation of Labor as well as annual reports, constitutions, and by-laws from the Albany, New York State, and national AFL-CIO. Memorandum and financial statements are also included.
  - Annual Reports, AFL CIO Local Labor Councils, 1990; 1998-1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 1)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 2)
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1996; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 3)
  - Endorsements, New York State, AFL CIO, 1996 and 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 4)
  - Financial Statements, 1986-1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 5)
  - Memoranda, 1984; 1987-1988; 1991-1998; 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 6)
  - Minutes, Agenda, and Communications, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 7)
  - Minutes, Agenda, and Communications, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 8)
  - Minutes, Agenda, and Communications, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 9)
  - Minutes, Agenda, and Communications, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 10)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 11)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 12)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 13)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 14)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 15)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 16)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 17)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 18)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 19)
  - Minutes and Communications, 1999 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 20)
  - Minutes and Communications, 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administrative Files), Folder 21)
- Subject Files, 1982-2000; 2; 1.0 cubic ft.
  In addition to news clippings on events important to labor unions, this series contains files on other events such as the remarks of speakers at awards dinners and dedications. Among the subjects documented are Award of Merit dinners for Josephine Sano.
  The video cassette recordings are productions of the experiences of workers at manufacturing plants. Deadly Corn is a 1990s production documenting the dangers of working at a manufacturing company. The series also includes designating petitions of the delegates to the 1984 Democratic National Convention.
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute Report and Polices, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Award of Merit Dinner, Capital District Union Label and Service Trades Council, AFL CIO, 1990-1993 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Award of Merit Dinner, Capital District Union Label and Service Trades Council, AFL CIO, 1994-1998 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Boy Scouts of America, AFL CIO, Community Services, Working, Serving, and Giving, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Capital District Labor History Project, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Capital District Labor Unions Charity Awards Dinner, 1993; 1996; 1998-1999 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Capital Region Career and Education Expo, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Catholic Social Teaching Letters to the Bishop, 1985 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Cornell Graduation Speech and Programs, Josephine Sano, 1982; 1985 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Deadly Corn, AIW Local 837's Campaign for Justice, VHS Tape, ca. 1994 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Delegates to National Convention, Designating Petitions, 1984 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Eastern New York Occupational Health Programs, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - NYSUT Task Force on Central Labor Councils, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Labor Day Parade Meeting Notes, 1984 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Managing Literacy Program Guidelines, New York State Education Department, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - New York State Assembly Labor Committee, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 1984-1992 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, 1993-2000; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - News Releases, 1987-1989; 1991-1992; 1995-1997 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - New York State Workplace Literacy Grant, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Occupational Retraining and Reemployment Act, Disclose Workers Program, Albany Colonie Regional Chamber of Commerce, 1988 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Remarks of Josephine Sano at the Dedication of Kate Mullaney House, 1998 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Remarks of Lane Kirkland at the Convention of Public Employee Department, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Remarks of Tom McGraw and Thomas Shea, 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Speech and Workshop Notes, Union Label and Service Trades Department of the State of New York, AFL CIO, 56th Convention, 2000 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Struggle in the Heartland, VHS Tape, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Teaching Labor Studies in Secondary School, Curriculum Guide for Teachers, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Testimony of the Union Producers and Programmers Network, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - University Employees Bulletin, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Veterans Employment and Training Program, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Worker Assistance Centers, New York State AFL CIO, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - Workplace Literacy Programs, Alcoholism & Hotel, Restaurant Employees Union, 1982; 1988 (Box 1 (2-Subject Files), Folder 32)
- Publications, 1965-2000; 3; 1.2 cubic ft.
  Among the publications in this series are the Federation, which communicated information on legislative bills that would affect union workers, the Capital Examiner, which relays information on business and labor communities, and the Legislative Gazette which also provided workers with information on union issues. Also included are reports of several New York State agencies.
  - AFL-CIO Third Annual Labor Recognition Dinner, 1987 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 1)
  - Annual Labor Recognition Dinner, AFL-CIO, 1985; 1987-1988 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 2)
  - Annual Labor Recognition Dinner, AFL-CIO, 1990; 1993 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 3)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, AFL-CIO, 1965; 1976; 1982-1993; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Brochures, New York State AFL-CIO, 1972-2000 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 5)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, 1970-1985; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 6)
  - Circa O.P.E. Convention Handbook, New York State AFL-CIO, 1998 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 7)
  - Constitutional Convention, New York State AFL-CIO, 1986; 1992 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 8)
  - Constitutional Convention, New York State AFL-CIO, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 9)
  - Handbook, Reports, and Research Papers, New York State AFL-CIO, 1986; 1988; 1990; Undated (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 10)
  - Labor Journals, 1985-1998 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 11)
  - Leadership Training Manual, AFL-CIO, 1987; 1989 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 12)
  - Leadership Training Manual, Current Issues, AFL-CIO Department of Education, 1991 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 13)
  - Legislative and Unemployment Insurance Programs, New York Labor Helping Work, 1989 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 14)
  - Magazines andReports, 1976 1995 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 15)
  - New York State AFL-CIO Unity, Newsletters, 1986-1994; 1996-1997; 1999 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 16)
  - New York State Association of Letter Carriers AFL-CIO, 2000 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 17)
  - New York State Capital Labor Parade, 1999 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 18)
  - New York State Department of Labor, Enforcements, 1994 (Box 1 (3-Publications), Folder 19)
  - Newsletters, 1981-1991 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 1)
  - Privatization, 1987; 1992 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 2)
  - Reports and Guidelines, AFL-CIO, 1985; 1987; 1997; Undated (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 3)
  - Reports on Labor, State of New York, 1989; 1991; 1998 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 4)
  - Taxes we can live with designing a system to meet future needs, New York State AFL CIO, 1991 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 5)
  - Worker Centered Learning: A Guide To Workplace Literacy, AFL-CIO Human Resources Department, 1990 (Box 2 (3-Publications), Folder 6)
- Activities, 1983-2000; 4; 0.20 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains information on the individual activities of the Albany Central Federation of Labor as well as the joint activities of the Albany Central Federation of Labor and other organizations. The series documents the first Workers Memorial Day, held in 1989, with fliers, posters, and other memorabilia.
  - Boycott Campaign against John Morrell Products, 1987 (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 1)
  - Conference and Convention Programs and Notes, 1983; 1986-1988; 1991-1999 (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 2)
  - Fliers and Publicity, 1986-2000; Undated (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 3)
  - New York State AFL-CIO/Central Labor Councils Training Conference, 1989 (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 4)
  - Posters, Undated (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 5)
  - President's Campaign Facts, Walter Mondale, 1984 (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 6)
  - PEF Contract, Rally Programs and Speech Notes, 1988 (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 7)
  - Voter Participation Worksheets, 1998 (Box 1 (4-Activities), Folder 8)
  - Workers Memorial Day Activities, 1990; 2000 (Oversized 1)
- Correspondence, 1983-2000; 5; 0.40 cubic ft.
  This series, composed almost entirely of Josephine Sano's correspondence, includes communications from Sano offering support and enlisting the support of several organizations. Correspondence in this series also illustrates differing points of view on particular issues between Sano and the state AFL-CIO. Much of the correspondence is between Sano and the New York state AFL-CIO.
  - Albany Central Federation of Labor, 1984-1991 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Albany Central Federation of Labor, 1992-2000; Undated (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, 1987; 1989-1991; 1993-1999 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Bishop's Office, Teachers, and Postal Workers, 1985-2000 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Labor Councils, New York State, 1984-1985; 1988-1999 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 5)
  - New York State, AFL CIO, 1983-1992 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - New York State, AFL CIO, 1993-1999 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - State of New York Executive Chamber, United States Congress, 1983-1999 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - State of New York Assembly, 1988-1994 (Box 1 (5-Correspondence), Folder 9)